http://youtu.be/DM3eO2Y8wgg
http://youtu.be/DM3eO2Y8wgg
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: In this video, let's
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: trong video này,
look up some information about our resistors.
hãy tìm hiểu thông tin về trở kháng.
Are resistors are carbon film.
Có phải trở kháng là lớp carbon mỏng?
The first thing let's look at is, what's inside of a resistor?
Đầu tiên hãy xem cái gì bên trong trở kháng?
We can see in this picture here that inside the resistor
Ta thấy trong hình này là những gì bên trong trở kháng
there is a carbon film.
có 1 lớp carbon mỏng.
It is this carbon film which affects or creates the resistance.
Lớp carbon này làm tăng trở kháng.
The next question I want to know is, how much power can I dissipate?
Câu hỏi kế tiếp, bao nhiêu công suất tôi có thể chịu được?
So I search the data sheet and look for the maximum power.
Tôi nhìn vào data sheet vào tìm công suất lớn nhất.
And it turns out what we have is a quarter-watt resistor.
Nó là điện trở 0.25 watt.
So the maximum amount of watts that this resistor can sustain is 1/4 watt.
Vậy số watt điện trở này có thể chịu được là 1/4 watt.
There are lots of places to look this up, but as you know,
Có nhiều chỗ bạn có thể kiếm được thông tin này, nhưng như bạn biết
resistors have color codes.
điện trở có các mã màu.
This data sheet will also show us the color codes.
Data sheet này cũng có mã màu.
Let's search for it.
Hãy kiếm nó.
Again, data sheets have lots of information.
Như thường lệ, data sheet có rất nhiều thông tin.
So it's important for you to have a goal while you're searching.
Quan trọng là bạn tìm thông tin gì.
And again, my goal is to find the color code.
Lần này tôi sẽ tìm mã màu.
There are two pieces of information in the color code.
Có 2 phần thông tin về mã màu.
The first is the tolerance and it turns out
Đầu tiên là dung sai
there we're probably going to have 5% tolerance.
lần này nó là 5%.
The second is the resistance itself.
Thứ 2 là trở kháng.
And as you can see from this diagram, that there
Nhìn vào biểu đồ này,
are three numbers and a fourth number which is the multiplier.
nó có 3 số, và số thứ 4 là bội số
So using these colors, we can look up what the resistance is.
Dùng những màu này, ta sẽ xác định được trở kháng là bao nhiêu.
And lastly, there's a resistance tolerance.
Cuối cùng là dung sai của trở kháng.
Like I said, we're probably going to have 5% resistors
Như tôi nói, đây là điện trở có dung sai 5%
and we'll see a gold band at the end.
và bạn sẽ thấy dãy màu vàng ở cuối.
So in summary, we've looked up how a resistor works, how much power it has,
Tóm lại, ta đã học điện trở hoạt động như thế này, công suất bao nhiêu,
and how do we search and look up the color codes of our resistors.
và làm cách nào để tìm và tính mã màu của điện trở.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: By the way, there's
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: dù gì
a lot of easy mnemonics people post on the internet for remembering these.
có nhiều thứ không cần phải nhớ trong thời đại internet
You're welcome to look up those, too.
bạn sẽ dễ dàng tìm thấy chúng.